Okay, בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is כ"ב, chaf bet,
בבא מציעא Bava Metzia 22, and we pick up at the bottom
of כ"א עמוד ב', chaf aleph amud bet, the last line, תא
שמע, tashma, and our learning should be in the זכות zechus of
the חיילים chayalim and חיילות chayalot and speedy return of the hostages
and a speedy end to the war.
Okay, תא שמע, tashma, we're in the middle of the debate of
אביי Abaye and רבא, Rava, whether יאוש שלא מדעת yeush shelo midaas
is יאוש yeush or not, where אביי Abaye says that it is
not יאוש yeush and רבא Rava says that it is יאוש. yeush.
The משנה mishna totally sounds like רבא Rava because all these cases
you can, if it's no סימן, siman, you can pick it up
and keep it. Maybe the owner didn't know about it, but we
assume that had he known, he would have been מיאש, miyash, therefore
you can keep it. And אביי Abaye explains all of those cases
or cases where we have good reason to assume the owner was
aware that they fell. So now we're going to keep on trying
to bring proofs to one side or the other. תא שמע, tashma,
last line of כ"א עמוד ב'. chaf aleph amud bet. הגנב שנטל
מזה ונתן לזה, Haganav shenatal mizeh venasan lazeh, if a burglar steals
from one person and gives it to another, sells it to another,
steals from Reuven gives it to Shimon. וכן גזלן שנטל מזה ונתן
לזה, Vechein gazlan shenatal mizeh venasan lazeh, or not a burglar, but
a גזלן, gazlan, somebody who does it out in the open, steals
from Reuven and gives it to Shimon. וכן ירדן שנטל מזה ונתן
לזה, Vechein Yarden shenatal mizeh venasan lazeh, or if it's not a
thief but the Jordan, some river washed away somebody's object and deposited
it in somebody else's yard.
מה שנטל נטל ומה שנתן נתן, Ma shenatal natal u'ma shenasan nasan,
what's done is done. What was taken was taken, what was given
was given, meaning that we can assume that there was יאוש, yeush,
יאוש ושינוי רשות, yeush v'shinui reshus, so the whole case of גנב
ganav and גזלן gazlan is of course what we did in בבא
קמא, Bava Kamma, and there if there's יאוש yeush in the hand
of the גנב ganav or גזלן gazlan and then it's given to
somebody else, יאוש ושינוי רשות yeush v'shinui reshus and the other person
takes possession
of
it. The question is going to be why are we assuming יאוש,
yeush, as you might remember from בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, there were
whole debates about whether סתם stam גנב ganav is יאוש, yeush, סתם
stam גזלן gazlan is יאוש. yeush. Let's take a look at what
the גמרא Gemara says.
בשלמא גזלן וירדן דחזי ליה ומיאש, Bishlama gazlan v'Yarden dechazi lei u'miyash,
I get the idea of
a גזלן gazlan and when the river washes it away, that's something
that the owner sees and is aware about. So therefore we can
assume you know in those circumstances he obviously would be מיאש. miyash.
אלא גנב מי קחזי ליה דמיאש, Ela ganav mi kachazi lei demiyash,
but a burglar, and assuming you know you could be aware of
a burglar after he leaves the house, you don't see him in
the act, but maybe we shouldn't always, how do we know that
the owner has found out yet? אלא גנב מי קחזי ליה, Ela
ganav mi kachazi lei, how does the owner didn't see him to
have יאוש? yeush? A burglar sells something to Shimon, we don't know
if Reuven found out about the burglary yet or not, and nevertheless
Shimon can keep it, we assume יאוש ושינוי רשות, yeush v'shinui reshus,
so that obviously seems to be evidence to רבא Rava that יאוש
שלא מדעת yeush shelo midaas counts as יאוש, yeush, since
had when the owner would find out, we would assume he would
be מיאש. miyash. So isn't that evidence to רבא? Rava? So תרגמה
רב פפא בלסטים מזוין, Targama Rav Pappa belistis mezuyan, that we're talking
about armed robbers, so it's out in the open, so it really
so the owner is aware of it. It's called a גנב, ganav,
you know that's a whole discussion in בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, does
that person have
the status of a גנב ganav because you know he would go
into hiding afterwards? It's very strange why exactly to call that a
גנב, ganav, but anyway that's not our issue, that's a בבא קמא
Bava Kamma issue. So it's not really talking about a גנב, ganav,
it's talking about an armed robber. So the גמרא Gemara says אי
הכי היינו גזלן, I hachi hainu gazlan, so okay that's really, meaning
not I get how you might technically be able to call it
a גנב, ganav, that's a בבא קמא Bava Kamma question, but why
would this discussion have to tell us these two you know two
scenarios? It's really just one scenario of a גזלן. gazlan. So the
גמרא Gemara says תרי גווני גזלן, Trei gavni gazlan, no it wants
to tell you both scenarios, you might have thought maybe in one
case there's more basis to say יאוש yeush than the other. But
it's not really talking about a גנב, ganav, it's talking about a
case the owner is aware. Again not at all the פשט pshat
but the גמרא Gemara is going to be okay with that answer.
Should be worth pointing out that this case is not one of
אבידה, aveda, it is one of יאוש, yeush, but it's about יאוש
yeush by גניבה וגזילה. gneiva v'gezeila. One could have imagined maybe the
parameters are different about יאוש שלא מדעת, yeush shelo midaas, but the
גמרא Gemara assumes it would be the same, at least they share
the idea that it's about the principle of יאוש ושינוי רשות. yeush
v'shinui reshus. תא שמע, tashma, come and hear, here's a תוספתא. Tosefta.
שטף נהר קוריו ועציו ואבניו, Shataf nahar korov v'etzav v'avanav, similar to
the thing we said before about the Jordan, a river wipes washes
away his beams and his wood and his stones, you know a
whole building project, and the river overflowed its banks washed it away,
ונתן לתוך שדה חבירו, venasan l’soch sadeh chavero, and deposited it in
his friend's field, just like the previous case. Just like the previous
case was describing, except a little more detail here. הרי אלו שלו
מפני שנתייאשו הבעלים. harei elu shelo mipnei shenityashu hab'alim.
You can keep it because the owners were definitely מיאש. meyaish. So
the גמרא Gemara understands you could have read that like רבא. Rava.
We would assume that when they would find out they would be
מיאש. meyaish. But that's not what it says, it says they were
מיאש. meyaish. So that means we actually, you know, they were aware
of it and therefore we automatically assume that they were מיאש. meyaish.
So the גמרא Gemara says טעמא דנתייאשו הבעלים. taama denityashu hab'alim. The
reason it's permissible is because there was active יאוש yeiush by the
owners, that they were aware. And we assume active יאוש. yeiush. הסתמא
לא? hastama lo? But it doesn't just say they're yours because they
would have been מיאש. meyaish. So it seems like even in a
scenario where when they knew they would be מיאש, meyaish, that's not
enough. You need active יאוש. yeiush. That seems to be case a
proof like אביי. Abaye. So the גמרא Gemara
says הכא במאי עסקינן כשיכול להציל. hacha bemai askinan kesheyachol lehatzil. No,
no, no. We're talking about a case here where you can't necessarily
assume יאוש. yeiush. The owner might be able to run after it
and grab it. So remember רבא'ס Rava's position was only when there
was no סימן. siman. When there was you could not auto when
you could automatically assume that he יאוש. yeiush. You knew he would
be מיאש meyaish when he would find out. This is not that
case. This is a case where he might be able to run
after it and grab it. So if he was unaware you can't
assume יאוש. yeiush. Maybe if he became aware he would try to
save it. So then in that case you need active יאוש yeiush
because you cannot assume יאוש yeiush would automatically happen in this case.
So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי אימא סיפא. ei hachi eima
seifa. Let's look at the end of this ברייתא. braita. אם היו
בעלים מרדפים אחריהם חייב להחזיר. im hayu bealim mardifim achareihem chayav lehachzir.
If the owners were running after them so they were demonstrating that
they were not מיאש, meyaish, they were trying to retrieve them, then
there's no יאוש yeiush and you have to return it. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute. אי ביכולים להציל מאי איריא מרדפין אפילו
אין מרדפין נמי. ei beyocholim lehatzil mai irya mardifim afilu ein mardifim
nami. So why do you need them to be actively running after
it? Meaning you went to extremes. If they were actively מיאש meyaish
you can keep it. If they're running after it you have to
return it. Well if the scenario is one where it's possible for
them to run after it and get it, right, then and we
can't assume יאוש, yeiush, then as long as there's no active יאוש
yeiush you should assume that they're not מיאש. meyaish. Why do you
need them to be actively running? If it's possible to retrieve it
then as long as there's no active יאוש yeiush it should be
we should assume that there is no יאוש. yeiush. It's like a
סימן. siman. So the גמרא Gemara says הכא
במאי עסקינן ביכולים להציל על ידי הדחק. hacha bemai askinan beyocholim lehatzil
al yedei hadechak. No, no, no. It's only if they really, really
put forth an effort will they be able to retrieve it. So
therefore מרדפין לא יאוש ייאש. mardifim lo yeiush yeiash. If they're choosing
to run after
it then we say ah, now clearly they're not מיאש. meyaish. אין
מרדפין יאוש מיאש. ein mardifim yeiush meyaish. If they're aware and don't
run after it that's saying eh, I'm not going to bother, it's
not worth the effort. So how does the גמרא Gemara explain the
scenario? The scenario is they it's possible for them to run and
to grab it. So that's like a סימן. siman. So if they're
unaware we cannot say oh, had they been aware they definitely would
have been מיאש. meyaish. You don't know. Had they been aware, even
if it would have taken real effort to run after it, some
people will expend the effort. So when they're unaware then we cannot
apply the principle for רבא Rava יאוש שלא מדעת הוי יאוש yeiush
shelo midaat havei yeiush because we don't know how they would react
when they found out. So that's the case the ברייתא braita is
not talking about, unaware. But because we don't know we can't assume
יאוש yeiush even according to רבא. Rava. The ברייתא braita is talking
about the case that they're aware. And therefore if they actively are
מיאש meyaish or even just don't say anything, which is the simple
sense of the ברייתא, braita, we assume יאוש. yeiush. They see it
and they're not bothering to run after it, we assume יאוש. yeiush.
Okay? But if they're actively running after it then we do know
then obviously they're not מיאש meyaish and then you cannot keep it.
Okay, so that's why it's not a challenge to רבא Rava because
we don't know for sure how they would react when they would
find out.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. תא שמע, ta shema,
come in here. כיצד אמרו התורם שלא מדעת תרומתו תרומה. keitzad amru
hatorim shelo midaat trumato truma. So this is a תוספתא בתרומות Tosefta
b'Trumos and it says sometimes if somebody takes תרומה truma for you
even if you're unawares, then the then it would can be good.
So the ברייתא braita says what's the scenario where that's true, that
somebody takes תרומה truma on your behalf and it works?
כיצד אמרו התורם שלא מדעת תרומתו תרומה. keitzad amru hatorim shelo midaat
trumato truma. הרי שירד לתוך שדה חברו וליקט ותרם. harei sheyarad letoch
sadeh chavero veliket vetaram. You שמעון Shimon went into ראובן'ס Reuven's field
and he gathered up the vegetables or he, you know, harvested the
grain. ותרם. vetaram. And he decided he would do ראובן Reuven a
favor so he took תרומה truma from the harvested grain. שלא ברשות.
shelo birshut. He didn't ask permission ahead of time. אם חושש משום
גזל אין תרומתו תרומה. im choshesh mishum gezel ein trumato truma. If
he's worried about stealing it's not a good תרומה. truma. It's ראובן
Reuven when he were to find out would be concerned like that
of theft. Now it doesn't mean theft like שמעון Shimon took it
and put it in his pocket, but it means that he would
not have wanted שמעון Shimon to have done that. He's afraid that
maybe שמעון Shimon gave too much grain or too nice grain for
תרומה. trumah. So if there's something that shows that he's not happy
with שמעון's Shimon behavior and שמעון Shimon might have acted inappropriately with
his property, then it's not good. אין תרומתו תרומה. ein trumaso trumah.
ואם לאו, v'im lav, but if he clearly shows that he has
no problem with what שמעון Shimon did, then תרומתו תרומה. trumaso trumah.
It's good. Okay, so now the ברייתא brayta continues to ask, how
do you know whether he's okay with what שמעון Shimon did or
not? ומנין הוא יודע אם חושש משום גזל ואם לאו U'minayin hu
yodea im choshesh mishum gezel v'im lav? How are you supposed to
know whether ראובן Reuven is concerned whether שמעון Shimon acted inappropriately with
his
property and used it in ways he wouldn't have wanted? So הרי
שבא בעל הבית ומצאו. harei she'ba ba'al habayis u'mitza'o. So you could
ask ראובן, Reuven, but even sometimes you don't have to ask him,
you can infer it. ראובן Reuven came and he found שמעון Shimon
there taking תרומה. trumah. He had just asked שמעון Shimon to harvest
the grain and here's שמעון Shimon taking תרומה. trumah. ואמר לו, V'amar
lo, and he says to him, כלך אצל יפות. cloch etzel yafos.
Why not take the better grain for תרומה? trumah? So the question
is, is he serious or is he sarcastic? So here's how we
know, in addition to tone of voice. אם נמצאו יפות מהן, Im
nimtzu yafos me'hen, if there actually was better grain to take, he
took medium quality grain for תרומה trumah and ראובן Reuven said to
him, "You should have used better quality grain." So if there genuinely
is better quality grain, we assume that ראובן Reuven is being sincere.
Then תרומתו תרומה. trumaso trumah. Then what שמעון Shimon did was in
line with what ראובן Reuven would have done.
It might not have been as good as ראובן Reuven wanted, but
it was not taking something inappropriate from ראובן. Reuven. It was consistent
enough with what ראובן Reuven would have done and the תרומה trumah
is good. ואם לאו, v'im lav, but if שמעון Shimon used the
best grain and ראובן Reuven said, "Ah, you should have used better
grain," clearly he's being sarcastic. He's saying, "Why did you use the
best
grain?" and that shows he's upset. So in that case אין תרומתו
תרומה. ein trumaso trumah. Then what שמעון Shimon did does not count.
It was clearly not what ראובן Reuven would have wanted. ליקטו הבעלים,
Liktu ba'alim, now let's say ראובן Reuven didn't say anything. He saw
that שמעון Shimon had taken תרומה trumah and then he went and
he gathered up for himself, like ליקטו liktu sounds more like vegetables
but I've been using grain which is a clear דאורייתא d'oraisa obligation
of תרומה, trumah, he went ahead and he also gathered vegetables or
did his own harvesting, ראובן Reuven did, והוסיפו עליהן, v'hosifu aleihen, and
he took his own תרומה trumah and he added it to שמעון's
Shimon תרומה. trumah. So that's obvious evidence that he's okay with what
שמעון Shimon did. In that case בין כך ובין כך תרומתו תרומה.
bein kach u'vein kach trumaso trumah. Even if he said, "Oh, you
should have taken better," and that was the best grain there was,
this action afterwards shows that at the end of the day he's
okay with what שמעון Shimon did. Anyway, this is all a case
where שמעון Shimon acted without ראובן's Reuven awareness and based on what
happens afterwards, we say if it's clear in hindsight that that's consistent
with what ראובן Reuven would have done, what ראובן Reuven would have
liked, then it's considered to have acted on ראובן's Reuven behalf, even
though ראובן Reuven never
expressed actively his דעת da'as at an earlier stage. So that seems
to be good evidence to רבא. Rava. So the גמרא gemara says
like this,
וכי נמצאו יפות מהן תרומתו תרומה, v'chi nimtzu yafos me'hen trumaso trumah,
so going to the line when if there is better grain then
ראובן Reuven was being sincere and then the תרומה trumah of שמעון
Shimon works. So the גמרא gemara says, אמאי, amai, why is that
true? הא בעידנא דתרם הא לא הוה ידע, Ha'be'idna d'taram ha lo
yavei yadi, when שמעון Shimon took the תרומה trumah ראובן Reuven was
still unaware, so it shows you that because we would say since
he would be okay when he found out, it's as if he's
okay at that moment. Otherwise, שמעון's Shimon taking תרומה trumah was without
any permission and any authority with ראובן. Reuven. So the fact that
we can be okay with it in hindsight shows a principle like
יאוש שלא מדעת הוי יאוש. yeush shelo m'da'as ha'vei yeush. Now there's
ways it's not exactly analogous which I'll discuss in a minute, but
anyway, that certainly seems pretty good evidence that you don't necessarily always
actively need the דעת da'as expressed at the time. So let's see
what the גמרא gemara answers. אמר רבא אליבא דאביי, Amar Rava aliba
d'Abaye, so רבא Rava now comes to the defense of אביי. Abaye.
This seems like a real
knockout proof with רבא, Rava, but רבא Rava says אביי Abaye has
a way that he can answer this. What could he say?
דשויוה שליח, D'shavyu shliach, we're talking that ראובן Reuven appointed שמעון Shimon
a שליח shliach to take תרומה. trumah. הכא נמי מסתברא, Hacha nami
mistavra, the גמרא gemara says that actually makes sense that we have
to be talking about a formal assigning of agency, a formal appointing
of שליחות, shlichus, דאי סלקא דעתך דלא שויוה שליח, d'isalka da'atach d'lo
shavyu shliach, if we're talking that שמעון Shimon just did it on
behalf of ראובן Reuven but without being formally appointed a
שליח, shliach, מי הויא תרומתו תרומה? mi havya trumaso trumah? How do
you know that? So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, והא אתם גם אתם אמר רחמנא לרבות שלוחכם
*Veha atem
gam atem amar rachmana lerabos shluchachem*. One of the core sources of
the principle of שליחות *shlichus*, of agency, is the פסוק *pasuk* by
תרומה trumah *truma* says, כן תרימו גם אתם תרומת השם *Ken tarimu
gam atem trumas Hashem*. So also you should take the תרומה trumah.
*truma*. Ah, so the word also you means not only you, but
somebody acting on your behalf. And from there we learn the principle
that you can make a שליח shaliach, *shaliach*, you can make an
agent to take תרומה trumah *truma* from you, for you. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying since we—so מה אתם לדעתכם *ma atem
l'da'atchem*, the same way when you take it it has to be
your consciously aware what you're doing, אף שלוחכם לדעתכם *af shluchachem l'da'atchem*.
So when you have an agent you have to consciously appoint an
agent. Somebody can't just step up and be your agent or act
for you on your behalf without you being aware. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is saying since this is the one of the sources
of שליחות *shlichus*, we can only be talking about a case where
ראובן *Reuven* actively appointed שמעון Shim'on *Shimon* a שליח *shaliach*. Now, that
is a very hard read of this ברייתא braisa *braisa*. First of
all, just because there's a principle of שליחות *shlichus* does not mean
that we're excluding the possibility that somebody could do it on behalf
of you even without being formally appointed as your שליח *shaliach*. Maybe
when you formally appoint them as your שליח *shaliach* they have more
license, you know, and whatever they do is okay, whereas if they're
acting on your behalf maybe it has to be more closely aligned,
you know, maybe there are other parameters. But just because שליחות *shlichus*
works doesn't mean, I don't think it has to mean that it's
not possible to have other ways in which you can take תרומה
*truma*. Besides which, the whole ברייתא braisa *braisa* says, how can—the whole
framing is התורם שלא מדעת *hatoram shelo mida'as*, taking תרומה *truma* without
the owner's awareness. And now we are actually saying that the scenario
is you actively, intentionally, it says מדעתכם *mida'atchem*, no, no, no, you
need מדעתכם *mida'atchem*. So it doesn't really mean שלא מדעת *shelo mida'as*.
It really means that you appointed him a שליח *shaliach*. And then
the ברייתא braisa *braisa* goes on and says, says, הרי הוא הולך
ותורם שלא
ברשות *harei hu holech v'soram shelo birshus*, without permission. So how could
we say that this ברייתא *braisa* is talking about a case of
שליחות *shlichus* if it describes it as שלא מדעת *shelo mida'as* and
שלא ברשות *shelo birshus*? It's an extremely hard read of the ברייתא
*braisa*. Presumably אביי Abaye. *Abaye* would say something like שלא מדעת *shelo
mida'as* and שלא ברשות *shelo birshus* means that the שליח *shaliach* did
not have clear license to take from this quality grain. He didn't
get clear parameters, you know, from the master, from the owner of
the grain. That might be what שלא מדעת *shelo mida'as* means, but
you know, שלא ברשות *shelo birshus*. Anyway, it's a very, very hard
read. Absolutely the ברייתא *braisa* implies that שמעון Shim'on *Shimon* did it
on his own, not being appointed a שליח *shaliach*, and it could
still work. Nevertheless, that's how רבא Rava *Rava* is answering on behalf
of אביי Abaye *Abaye*, all talking about שליחות *shlichus* and the question
is when is the שליח *shaliach* can be assumed to operate within
the parameters that the owner is okay with.
Okay, so now let's—the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will continue. אלא הכא במאי
עסקינן *Ela hacha bemai askinan*, what are we talking about? כגון דשוייה
שליח *kegon d'shavyei shliach*, he appointed him a שליח *shaliach*, ואמר ליה
זיל תרום *v'amar lei zil trum*, go take תרומה *truma*, ולא אמר
ליה תרום מהני *v'lo amar lei trum mehani*, okay, and he didn't
say where exactly to take תרומה *truma* from. וסתמיה דבעל הבית כי
תרם מבינונית תרם *V'stamei d'ba'al habayis ki saram m'beinonisa saram*, and we
should normally assume that the owner wants תרומה *truma* taken from the
average grain, not the bad one, not the particularly choice stuff, the
average stuff. ואזל איהו ותרום מיפות *V'azal ihu v'saram miyofos*, and then
שמעון *Shimon* went and he took תרומה *truma* from the higher quality
grain. ובא בעל הבית ומצאו ואמר ליה כלך אצל יפות *Uva ba'al
habayis umatz'o v'amar lei kolach eitzel yofos*, the owner came and found
him and said to him, you should have gotten from the best
quality. אם נמצאו יפות מהן תרומתו תרומה *Im nimtz'u yofos mehen trumaso
truma*, if there is actually even higher quality, then the owner was
not being—wasn't being sarcastic, he was being sincere, and it's in line
with the owner, and it works. ואם לאו אין תרומתו תרומה *V'im
lav ein trumaso truma*, and if not, no. Okay, so that's what
now the שלא ברשות *shelo birshus* and שלא מדעת *shelo mida'as* means—that
we should have assumed that the owner wanted you to do from
average, and you operated שלא מדעת *shelo mida'as* and שלא ברשות *shelo
birshus* by taking from higher quality. But the whole case is a
case of שליח *shaliach*, and therefore what we're just trying to prove
is that it is within the parameters of the שליחות *shlichus* when
you did something that would normally be beyond what we would normally
have expected the owner would have intended.
Okay, so we've really gone through many, many cases, a few support
אביי Abaye *Abaye*, the vast number of them support רבא Rava *Rava*,
and through various rereadings and twists, you know, by our משנה *Mishna*
we say you're aware that it fell, even though it sounds like
the, you know, there's no reason to assume the owner was aware,
but we explained that that... the case. And by this case of
תרומה we say also, there's a special case, he appointed him שליח,
not what it sounds like that שמעון just acted on his own.
Now it is worth pausing for a moment and pointing out that
this is the first case in the proofs that's not about a
case of יאוש. ye'ush. We had one case before a גניבה gneiva
וגזילה, gezeila, but at least that was יאוש. ye'ush. This is not
about יאוש, ye'ush, which is important because you could have said that
רבא'ס Rava's principle of יאוש שלא מדעת הוי יאוש ye'ush shelo mada'at
havi ye'ush is not some general כל התורה kol haTorah principle that
when somebody would have a certain frame of mind that we assume
that we treat as if that's already their frame of mind. It
could have been a principle about אבידה, aveida, when is the אבידה
aveida considered enough out of the control of the owner? If he
both physically lost it and the circumstances are such that he would
normally have no reasonable expectation of getting it back. But clearly the
גמרא Gemara is not understanding that it's a specific מציאה metzia idea
and it's reading רבא Rava to say that when something is about
your desire, your frame of mind, what you want, maybe רבא Rava
would say we're prepared to say what your frame of mind is
based on what it would be when you would find out. I
do have to say that even that is a big חדוש, chiddush,
the תרומה case, because if you remember the גמרא Gemara said when
it's a סימן, siman, even if you have יאוש ye'ush at the
end we don't read it backwards because we wouldn't have said automatically
you would have been מיאש. miya'esh. We only know you're מיאש miya'esh
now. You could have said the same here. We don't know if
the owner would be okay with what שמעון did. So maybe רבא
Rava would have only said הוי יאוש havi ye'ush when we could
absolutely be certain that the owner would be מיאש miya'esh when he
would find out. This is a case where it's up for question
and it's only based on how he reacts after do we can
we speculate that that's what he would have thought before. So it
is interesting that this case both proves the גמרא Gemara thinks רבא
Rava, applies more broadly and also that we are sometimes willing to
act look retroactively even when we would not have been certain how
he would have reacted at the time. Okay, let's see what the
גמרא Gemara does next.
Okay, so first wide line. אמימר מר זוטרא ורב אשי. Ameimar Mar
Zutra ve'Rav Ashi. אמימר מר זוטרא ורב אשי איקלעו לבוסתנא דמרי בר
איסק. Ameimar Mar Zutra ve'Rav Ashi iklu l'bustana d'Mari bar Isak. They
came to the garden of מרי בר איסק. Mari bar Isak. אייתי
אריסיה, Aiti arisei, so the sharecropper of מרי בר איסק Mari bar
Isak came and he brought תמרי ורמוני, tamrei v'rimonei, dates and
pomegranates, ושדא קמייהו v'shada kmaihu and threw it in front of them,
presented them: oh, you're some honored rabbis, here have some dates and
pomegranates from the garden. And it seems clear from the context that
these were not the ones that the sharecropper had rights to by
being a sharecropper; these were from the trees of the portion of
the owner of the field. אמימר ורב אשי אכלי. Ameimar ve'Rav Ashi
achli. אמימר Ameimar and רב אשי Rav Ashi ate it. They probably
figured we're important rabbis, we're friends with the owner, of course he
would be okay with us having from his fruit. מר זוטרא לא
אכל. Mar Zutra lo achal. מר זוטרא Mar Zutra said: I don't
know, he didn't give permission, I want to make sure I won't
eat the owner's fruit unless the owner very much gives it to
me; I'm not just going to assume he would be okay with
me eating it. מר זוטרא לא אכל. Mar Zutra lo achal. אדהכי
אתא מרי בר איסק. Ad'hachi ata Mari bar Isak. So when they
were in the middle of this, some were eating and some were
not, מרי בר איסק Mari bar Isak came along. אשכחינהו, Ashkachinhu, he
found them that they had come to visit and that they were
eating this fruit, ואמר ליה לאריסיה, V'amar lei l'arisei, and he said
to his sharecropper: אמאי לא אייתית להו לרבנן מהנך שפירתא. Amai lo
ayiteis lehu l'rabbanan me'hanech shapirta. Why didn't you give these חשוב chashuv
rabbis only this average grain, average dates and pomegranates? You should have
given them the best quality. אמר להו, Amar lehu, and presumably there
was better quality fruit. So this seems very parallel to our case
by תרומה. But even afterwards it'll be clear, מר
זוטרא Mar Zutra still refused to eat even after the owner had
that reaction. So אמר ליה אמימר ורב אשי למר זוטרא. Amar lei
Ameimar ve'Rav Ashi l'Mar Zutra. So אמימר Ameimar and רב אשי Rav
Ashi said to מר זוטרא: Mar Zutra: השתא אמאי לא אכיל מר,
Hashta amai lo achil mar, now that the owner has said why
didn't you give them the better, now you should eat. It's clear
that he's okay with us eating the fruit. והתניא ותנן בברייתא Ve'hatanya
u'tnan b'braisa נישוף יפות מהן תרומתו תרומה nishuf yafot meihen trumato trumah
that if there's better quality it's good, so the owner showed there
is better quality fruit, so the owner showed he's okay with us
eating this, he even wanted us to have the better fruit. Why
are you still refusing to eat? אמר להו, Amar lehu, he said
to them: הכי אמר רבא. hachi amar Rava. Here's what רבא Rava.
said: לא אמרו כלפי יפות אלא לענין תרומה בלבד. lo amru kelapei
yafot ela l'inyan trumah bilvad. When do we assume that when he's
saying you should have taken the better that he's being sincere and
not being sarcastic? When we're dealing with תרומה משום דמצוה הוא. mishum
de'mitzvah hu. It's a מצוה. mitzvah. וניחא ליה v'nicha lei and Therefore,
we're pre-inclined to assume that somebody would have wanted to do it
in the best way and would have wanted to give, you know,
the highest quality if there is a better quality. So if there
is a better quality, we will read his statement as a sincere
one because that's what we're going to assume people's approach will be
by doing a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* by doing תרומה *terumah*. But here,
אבל הכא *aval hacha* in our case, משום כסיפותא הוא דאמר הכי
*mishum kesifuso hu de'amar hachi*. Now, you could have said, you know,
it's a מצוה *mitzvah* to feed these important rabbis, but there's another
factor here. He's embarrassed to say—what's he going to do? He's going
to yell at his sharecropper in our presence and say 'Why did
you give them my fruit? I don't want—they shouldn't be eating my
fruit.' No. He's actually constrained and embarrassed and he's now going to
say 'Oh, you should have given them even better stuff' because, you
know, so he looks good right now. But that doesn't mean he's
really okay with it. So in this context, you cannot assume that
when he said 'you should have given them better' even if there
was better, that he was being sincere. He might have said it
because he felt pressured to say that given the circumstances. Okay, that
was a nice little application or non-application of that case of תרומה
*terumah*. Now we're going back to trying to prove אביי Abaye *Abaye*
and רבא Rava. *Rava* one way or the other. תא שמע Ta
shema, *Ta shema* come and hear.
This is a תוספתא *Tosefta* in מכשירין *Machshirin*. הודח בטל עליהן ושמח
הרי זה בכי יותן *Hodeiah tal aleihen vesamach harei zeh bechiyutan*. So
the הלכה halacha *halacha* is the following. All food only becomes susceptible
to become טמא *tamei*—not become טמא *tamei* but able to become טמא
*tamei*—after it comes in contact with liquid. If it's stuff that grows
from the ground, obviously it's coming in contact with liquid—the rain, the
dew—but after
it's been cut from the ground, after it's been picked or harvested,
then if it remains totally dry, even if it touches טומאה *tumah*,
it's something טמא *tamei* it does not become טמא *tamei*, only after
it's been in contact with liquid, now can it become טמא *tamei*.
And there are seven particular liquids, but water is the most obvious.
Now, the הלכה halacha *halacha* is, it's based on a פסוק *pasuk*
in the תורה *Torah* that says וכי יותן מים על זרע *vechi
yutan mayim al zera*, when water is placed on a seed, and
then it speaks about it becoming טמא *tamei*.
So the הלכה *halacha* is that—and we'll see in a minute—that the
word יותן *yutan* is written without the ואו *vav*.
So it could also be read as יתן *yiten*, place on it.
So is it that water has to actively be placed on it,
or even if it just fell on it accidentally without intent? And
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* comes—the הלכה *halacha* is a combination of
the two. It could be the liquid got onto the fruit or
food without the intent of the owner. That's יותן *yutan*, it happened.
But it only will make the seeds—will do a הכשר hechsher *hechshar*,
make it susceptible for becoming טמא *tamei*, if the owner is ניחא
ליה nicha leh, *nichla lei*, he's glad that it became wet, it's
something it keeps the food moist or whatever, דומיא דכי יתן *dumya
dechiyiten*. It has to be as if he put it, similar to
putting it on, it's something that he likes. So the water, the
liquid could have gotten on completely without him being unaware and it
will be הכשר *hechshar* if it's a situation in which he is
ניחא ליה nicha leh *nichla lei*, he's glad that it happened. So
let's take a look. תא שמע *Ta shema*. הודח בטל עליהן *Odei
hu tal aleihen*. So somebody had his fruit up on the roof
drying out and in the—the dew condensed on it in the morning
and he's going up to the roof and bringing it down. If
when the dew is still on the fruit he sees it ושמח
*vesamach* and he's happy, he's glad—'Oh good, it's got moist, it got
wet'—he's happy about the situation, הרי זה בכי יותן *harei zeh bechiyutan*,
then that satisfies if water comes in contact now it is susceptible
to becoming טמא *tamei*. However, and obviously if he's not happy it
wouldn't. But here's a more interesting case.
נגבו *Nagvu*, if they got dried after the—after the dew was wiped
off, אף על פי ששמח *af al pi shesamach*, he is happy
that the dew fell on them, but he only became aware and
only expressed that he was glad about it after it had already—the
dew had already been dried off of it. Now, top of כ"ב
עמוד ב' *chaf bet amud bet*, אינה בכי יותן *eina bechiyutan*, then
it is not susceptible. Okay, so that actually seems like a proof
like אביי Abaye. *Abaye*. Here he was happy afterwards, but because he
wasn't actively happy when the dew was on it, it doesn't count.
Again, I should note this is not a case of יאוש *ye'ush*,
it's not a case of אבידה *aveidah*, we're making רבא Rava, *Rava*
more broad. So now let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says.
טעמא מאי *Ta'ama mai*, what's the reason that if he's happy afterwards,
when he finds out later after the dew has been dried off,
why does it not work? לאו משום דלא אמרינן כיון דאיגלאי מילתא
דהשתא ניחא ליה nicha leh, מעיקרא נמי ניחא ליה nicha leh *Lav
mishum delo amrinan kivan de'igla melsa dehasta nichla lei me'ikara nami nichla
lei*? We don't say—and here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* nicely abstracts this
concept of יאוש שלא מדעת yeiush shelo mada'as? *ye'ush shelo midas*, how
you would apply it across categories. Since now it's clear that he
was happy... we treat it, or we say he was happy with
it before, and we treat it as if he were actively happy
with it earlier. Based on what we see now is דעת, daas,
we retroactively say that would have been his frame of mind, that
was his frame of mind before, even though he wasn't conscious or
aware to have that reaction. All right, so you see, we don't
say that. And therefore, even though he's happy now, we don't apply
it to when it was still moist. And that shows you like
אביי. Abaye So the גמרא Gemara says no. שאני התם דכתיב כי
יתן עד שיתן. Shani hasam d'chsiv ki yiten ad she'yiten.
There it's a special הלכה about הכשר that you have to actively,
consciously place the water on the seed. So the גמרא Gemara says
אי הכי רישא נמי? ei hachi reisha nami? So wait, you don't
have to actively place the water on the seed? We said even
if the dew fell, if you were happy, that's okay. It doesn't
need the active act of the owner. No, התם כדרב פפא. hasam
k'dirav Pappa.
The explanation is like רב פפא. Rav Pappa. This is what I
said before, דרב פפא רמי, d'Rav Pappa rami, רב פפא Rav Pappa
showed a contradiction. כתיב כי יתן, ksiv ki yiten, the verse is
written כי יתן, ki yiten, there's no ו, vov, so you could
read it כי יתן, ki yiten, וקרינן כי יותן. v'krinan ki yutan.
But we read it, the מסורת'ס masores's to read it when water
is placed, not when you place water. הא כיצד? ha keitzad? How
do we combine those two? בעינן כי יותן דומיא דכי יתן. ba'inan
ki yutan dumya d'ki yiten. You need it's כי יותן ki yutan
is enough, that water falls on it, liquid falls on it, you
know, on its own, but only when it is as if, similar
to as if you consciously put it on. מה יתן לדעת אף
כי יותן נמי לדעת. ma yiten l'da'as af ki yutan nami l'da'as.
And the same way when you place it, that's something you're doing
conscious, and normally we say what that means is that you have
to be ניחא ליה, want it, the same way when you actively
put something on liquid on you want it. But now we're going
beyond just ניחא ליה and we're saying לדעת. l'da'as. When you actively
do something, when you put the water on, you have to be
conscious of what you're doing. So here too the הלכה is it'll
happen even if the dew falls by itself, but it has to
be similar to כי יתן ki yiten and it has to be
similar in two ways. Number way you have to be happy with
it, ניחא ליה, and number
that maybe we could have applied רבא, Rava. but number two, it
has to be לדעת. l'da'as. The same way when you actively put
water you're conscious of it, when here too it has to be
ניחא ליה and you have to be conscious of it while the
liquid is on it, you have to be conscious of it and
only then is it like you actively put it on. It's not
enough to have a frame of mind, a virtual frame of mind.
So that's a special case and therefore that would not be a
contradiction to רבא. Rava תא שמע, come in here. דאמר רבי יוחנן
משום רבי ישמעאל בן יהוצדק, d'amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yishmael ben
Yehotzadak, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said in the name of רבי ישמעאל
בן יהוצדק, Rabbi Yishmael ben Yehotzadak, מנין לאבדה ששטפה נהר שהיא מותרת?
minayin l'aveidah sheshatafah nahar shehi muteres? How do you know that if
a lost object, you know, some thing was washed away by the
ocean, by the river—we had these cases before—that it is permissible? And
meaning we'll see in a minute permissible even with a סימן, siman,
even if the owner says he's לא מייאש, lo me'ayeish, the fact
that it is out of the reach of anybody makes it objectively
lost to you, lost to the world and therefore totally now free
to whoever gets it. דכתיב וכן תעשה לחמורו וכן תעשה לשמלתו וכן
תעשה לכל אבדת אחיך אשר תאבד ממנו ומצאתה. d'chsiv v'chein ta'aseh lachamoro
v'chein ta'aseh l'simlaso v'chein ta'aseh l'chol aveidas achicha asher tovad mimenu umetzasah.
So you should do to his donkey and to his garment, and
so you shall do to all lost objects of your brother אשר
תאבד ממנו asher tovad mimenu that will be lost from him ומצאתה
umetzasah and you find it, that you have an obligation to return.
So the גמרא says מי שאבודה ממנו ומצויה אצל כל אדם. mi
she'avudah mimenu umetzuyah eitzel kol adam. The word תאבד ממנו, tovad mimenu,
lost from him, means that it's he doesn't... he's lost it, but
other people have access to it. He doesn't remember where he put
it, but everybody who walks by, you know, it's right there, it's
right there, you know, in Central Park. Everybody sees it. He lost
it, but it's accessible to others. That's a type of an אבדה
aveidah that you have an obligation to return. יצאת זו שאבודה ממנו
ואינה מצויה אצל כל אדם yatzas zu she'avudah mimenu v'eina metzuyah eitzel
kol adam to exclude the case of being washed away by the
river, שאבודה ממנו ואינה מצויה אצל כל אדם. she'avudah mimenu v'eina metzuyah
eitzel kol adam. It's lost to everybody, nobody has access to it.
It might eventually get washed up, but right now it's out of
everybody's reach. So something that's אבודה ממנו ומכל אדם, avuda mimenu umikol
adam, lost to all people, that completely breaks the connection to the
owner and it is free for whoever finds it. Even if there's
a סימן, siman, even if he says he's not מייאש, me'ayeish, it
doesn't matter; objectively that breaks the connection. So now the גמרא says,
okay, what does that have to do with יאוש שלא מדעת? So
he says this: ואיסורא דומיא דהיתירא. v'isura dumya d'heteira.
Now the case of forbidden, meaning when there is an obligation to
return, we should see as an analogy to this case when there's
no obligation to return. מה היתירא בין דאית ביה סימן בין דלית
ביה סימן. mah heteira bein d'is beih siman bein d'leis beih siman.
This case of אבודה ממנו ומכל אדם avuda mimenu umikol adam is
whether the thing has a סימן siman or doesn't have a סימן.
siman. Right? The fact that it's out of everybody's reach makes it
permissible even with a סימן. siman. So if that's true about the
case that it's totally permissible,
so the same way in this case... בין דאית ביה סימן בין
דלית ביה סימן שרא, bein d'is bei siman bein d'leis bei siman
shara, whether with or without a סימן siman it's permissible, אף איסורא,
af issura, the case where it's forbidden for people to take it,
there's a מצוה to return it, which is when it's מצוי אצל
כל אדם. metzuy etzel kol adam. He left it in Central Park
and now there's a and people he lost it in Central Park
and now people have an obligation to return it because they have
access to it. So that should be a similar scenario. אף איסורא
בין דאית ביה סימן בין דלית ביה סימן אסורא, af issura bein
d'is bei siman bein d'leis bei siman assura,
whether with a סימן siman or without a סימן siman they can't
take it, they have to return it. So with a סימן siman
we understand why they have to return it. Why would they have
to return it without a סימן? siman? That only works if we
say like אביי that even without a סימן siman you cannot, you
start by assuming it's not you have to return it until you
actively hear the owner being מייאש. meyayesh. Okay, so that does not
seem of all the evidence, this is just by parallel analogy. Since
the case it's permissible is with or without a סימן siman when
it's lost to everybody, then when it's forbidden it's also with or
without a סימן siman and even without a סימן siman it's forbidden
until you hear ייאוש. yeush. Really? Is that evidence that clear that
that's what that ברייתא is saying? But somehow the גמרא is very
happy with this and the גמרא says תיובתא דרבא תיובתא. tiyufta d'Rava
tiyufta. That is an absolute contradiction to רבא. Rava So it's quite
funny, if you ask me, all the evidence was like רבא, Rava.
all the strong evidence, but it seems like this is the conclusion
the גמרא wanted to reach, so it's reading this ברייתא as an
absolute proof against רבא. והלכתא כוותיה דאביי ביע"ל קג"ם. v'hilchisa k'vosei d'Abaye
b'yaal kegam.
And this probably was why the גמרא wanted to get there to
show
that it's a contradiction to רבא because we say we have a
tradition that we normally rule like רבא against אביי except in six
cases which are indicated by the mnemonic יע"ל קג"ם. yaal kegam. What
do they stand for? So the יוד yud is ייאוש שלא מדעת.
yeush shelo madaas. We rule like אביי לא הוי ייאוש, lo havei
yeush, you need conscious דעת, daas. conscious ייאוש, yeush, we don't retroactively
assume or even if we say you would have been מייאש meyayesh
definitely, doesn't matter, you need conscious דעת. ייאוש שלא מדעת yeush shelo
madaas we rule like אביי. עין ayin is a case of עדות
שיכול אתה להזימה, eidus sheyachol ata l'hazimah,
excuse me, עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, excuse me, not that, עדים זוממים
למפרע הוא נפסל, edim zomemim l'mafrea hu nifsal, a question whether when
somebody is found an עדים זוממים edim zomemim they only become פסול
לעדות pasul l'eidus. from that point on or retroactively. The למד lamed
is לחי העומד מאליו, lechi haomed me'elav, what counts as a type
of a post to make a courtyard okay to carry in. The
קוף kuf is קידושין שלא נמסרו לביאה, kiddushin shelo nimseru l'biah, if
there's a קידושין kiddushin which cannot be consummated הלכתית halachicly because it's
prohibited, is that a legitimate קידושין, kiddushin, is that חל? chal? The
גימל gimmel is מה הגימל? ma ha'gimmel? Oh, גילוי דעת בגט, gilui
daas b'get, which is actually similar, do we try to read somebody's
intent when they're trying to like מבטל mevatel a גט get or
something of that nature? And the מם mem is מומר אוכל נבילות
לתיאבון, mumar ochel neveilos l'tei'avon, לתיאבון או להכעיס, l'tei'avon o l'hachis, whether
somebody who does an איסור דאורייתא issur d'oraisa but not related to
monetary matters are they פסול pasul לעדות. l'eidus In all those cases
we rule like אביי against רבא. That is the גמרא'ס Gemara's conclusion
based on this last ברייתא which does not seem so strong, but
anyway, the גמרא clearly wants to come to this conclusion.